Today we are going to talk about a topic that everyone may have a sense of.
今天我們要談論一個每個人可能都有所感受的話題。
When you work with AI, do you have a feeling that you are just using it and not really working with it?
當你使用AI時，你是否有一種感覺，就是你只是在使用它，而不是真正與它合作？
In today's content, we are going to talk about how to master the so-called tail art.
在今天的內容中，我們將談論如何掌握所謂的提示藝術。
Turn AI from a tool to your real strategic partner.
將AI從一個工具轉變為你真正的戰略夥伴。
Yes, this is where the question is, right?
是的，這就是問題所在，對吧？
Many of us are thinking every day about how to hand things over to AI
我們很多人每天都在思考如何將事情交給AI
so that it can really help,
以便它能真正提供幫助，
not make more trouble for me on the contrary.
而不是反過來給我帶來更多麻煩。
This is really a big question.
這真的是個大問題。
But there is an opinion here that I think may surprise you.
但這裡有一個觀點，我認為可能會讓你驚訝。
Look at what this sentence says.
看看這句話說了什麼。
It says that the timing of good tail art has actually nothing to do with AI.
它說好的提示藝術的時機實際上與AI無關。
The key is your own professional knowledge.
關鍵是你自己的專業知識。
Hey, this is interesting.
嘿，這很有趣。
After a long time, the key is not the AI technology itself, but ourselves.
經過長時間思考，關鍵不是AI技術本身，而是我們自己。
What the hell is this?
這到底是什麼意思？
Let's take a look.
讓我們來看看。
Okay, how do we understand this?
好的，我們如何理解這一點？
In fact, we can look at it as a framework.
實際上，我們可以將其視為一個框架。
It's the so-called AI tail art three pillars.
這就是所謂的AI提示藝術三支柱。
With this structure, we can understand this concept step by step.
有了這個結構，我們可以逐步理解這個概念。
These three pillars are actually linked together.
這三支柱實際上是相互關聯的。
The first one is called problem awareness.
第一個叫做問題意識。
The white line is that you have to figure out what you want to do first.
要點是你首先要弄清楚你想做什麼。
Then the second one is platform awareness.
然後第二個是平台意識。
You have to understand what weapons you have and how powerful they are.
你必須理解你有什麼武器，它們有多強大。
Finally, it's the mission tail.
最後，它是任務提示。
That is, how smart to divide the work.
也就是說，如何聰明地分配工作。
Sounds like it's not hard, right?
聽起來不難，對吧？
But the devil is hidden in the details.
但魔鬼隱藏在細節中。
Let's take a look one by one.
讓我們逐一看看。
Okay, let's take a look at the first step.
好的，讓我們看看第一步。
Start from yourself.
從你自己開始。
You might think it's weird.
你可能會覺得這很奇怪。
Isn't it talking about AI?
不是在談論AI嗎？
How could it start from yourself?
怎麼會從你自己開始呢？
That's the point.
這正是重點。
What is this so-called problem awareness?
這個所謂的問題意識是什麼？
To be honest, before you open any AI tool,
老實說，在你打開任何AI工具之前，
you have to figure out the entire blueprint in your head.
你必須在你的腦海中想清楚整個藍圖。
What is your goal?
你的目標是什麼？
What things do you need to achieve your goal?
你需要做什麼事情來達成你的目標？
It's kind of like building a house.
這有點像建造一棟房子。
You have to have a design picture in your hand.
你必須手裡拿著一張設計圖。
Otherwise, no matter how hard you look for an AI worker,
否則，無論你怎麼努力去尋找一個 AI 工作者，
he won't be able to build the house you want, right?
他也無法建造你想要的房子，對吧？
So how do you train this problem awareness?
那麼你如何培養這種問題意識呢？
It's actually very simple.
其實非常簡單。
It's just that you stop and take a deep breath.
就是你停下來，深呼吸一口氣。
Then ask yourself a few questions.
然後問自己幾個問題。
For example, what exactly do I want to accomplish?
例如，我到底想要完成什麼？
How does this project work?
這個專案是如何運作的？
And most importantly,
最重要的是，
what parts of the project do I need to use my expertise to make critical decisions?
專案中的哪些部分需要我用我的專業知識來做出關鍵決定？
Think about these questions first.
先思考這些問題。
The foundation for your cooperation with AI is the real answer.
你與 AI 合作的基礎就是這些真實的答案。
So you see,
所以你看，
this goes back to what we just said.
這又回到了我們剛才說的。
Those who really use AI well,
那些真正善於使用 AI 的人，
they are actually experts in their own field first.
他們首先實際上是自己領域的專家。
Then they are the messengers of AI.
然後他們才是 AI 的傳遞者。
Don't forget that your own professional knowledge
別忘了你自己的專業知識
is the biggest and most irreplaceable weapon in your hands.
是你手中最大、最不可替代的武器。
OK, so the first step is to figure out your own goal first.
好的，所以第一步是先搞清楚你自己的目標。
What about after the goal is clear?
那在目標明確之後呢？
The second step,
第二步，
let's take a look at what tools you have in your armory.
讓我們看看你軍械庫裡有什麼工具。
This step,
這一步，
we call it platform awareness.
我們稱之為平台意識。
Its meaning is actually very simple.
它的意思其實非常簡單。
You don't have to become a super strong engineer.
你不必成為一個超強的工程師。
But you have to be like a great chef.
但你必須像一位偉大的廚師。
A good chef will be very clear about which knife and which pot he has in his kitchen.
一位好廚師會非常清楚他廚房裡有哪把刀和哪口鍋。
Which knife is suitable for cutting sashimi?
哪把刀適合切刺身？
Which pot is suitable for boiling soup?
哪口鍋適合煮湯？
You just have to use this mentality to understand the temperament and ability of each AI tool in your hand.
你就用這種心態去理解手中每個 AI 工具的脾氣和能力。
So here's the question.
那麼問題來了。
How do you establish this platform awareness?
你如何建立這種平台意識呢？
Let me tell you,
讓我告訴你，
there is no shortcut.
沒有捷徑。
Just one word, play.
只要一個詞，就是體驗。
You just have to go down and try it yourself.
你只需要自己去嘗試一下。
If you play for a long time, you will find that some AI is really like a sports car.
如果你長時間玩，你會發現有些 AI 真的就像跑車一樣。
The speed is super fast, but it may not be so stable.
速度超快，但可能不那麼穩定。
Some of them are like a truck running slowly but very reliable.
有些則像卡車，跑得慢但非常可靠。
You can only find the tools that are most suitable for your work process by experiencing them yourself.
只有通過自己的親身體驗，才能找到最適合你工作流程的工具。
Then slowly build your own AI weapon.
然後慢慢建立你自己的 AI 武器庫。
OK, so you see,
好的，所以你看，
our platform is ready,
我們的平台已經準備好了，
we are familiar with the tools.
我們也熟悉了工具。
Now we finally come to the most critical step.
現在我們終於來到了最關鍵的一步。
How do we smartly arrange our troops?
我們如何聰明地部署我們的力量呢？
That is, how to fail the task.
也就是說，如何分配任務。
I think this task is more like an art than a science.
我認為這個任務更像一門藝術而不是科學。
It's definitely not that you just throw your work to AI and it's fine.
絕對不是說你只是把工作扔給 AI 就完事了。
It's not.
並不是這樣。
It's more like a conductor of a band.
更像是樂隊的指揮。
You have to be very clear.
你必須非常清楚。
When should we let the violinist,
什麼時候應該讓小提琴手，
that is, us humans,
也就是我們人類，
play a wonderful solo?
演奏一段精彩的獨奏？
When should we let the drummer,
什麼時候應該讓鼓手，
that is, AI,
也就是 AI，
come out and drive the rhythm of the whole band?
出場並推動整個樂隊的節奏？
Hey, look at this picture.
嘿，看看這張圖。
It makes this strategic division very clear.
它清楚地展示了這個戰略劃分。
The left is the task that we humans are responsible for.
左邊是由我們人類負責的任務。
You see, like what is the key judgment,
你看，比如什麼是關鍵判斷，
strategic vision,
戰略遠見，
and the most important responsibility.
以及最重要的責任。
These tasks require high thinking and judgment.
這些任務需要高度的思考和判斷。
Of course, we still have to do it ourselves.
當然，我們還是得自己做。
The right is the task that is suitable for AI.
右邊是適合 AI 做的任務。
For example, it takes a lot of time.
例如，耗時很長的工作。
It takes a lot of data to integrate,
需要整合大量數據的，
or some more routine interactions.
或一些更常規的互動。
So simply put,
簡單來說，
the rule is that we need to move our brains,
原則是我們需要動腦，
and we need to be responsible for ourselves.
我們需要對自己負責。
Those more repetitive actions
那些更重複性的動作
can be entrusted to AI.
可以委託給 AI。
So you will find that the so-called tail is not actually
所以你會發現，所謂的尾部實際上並不
a switch that gives or does not give.
是一個給予或不給予的開關。
You can imagine it as a canvas.
你可以把它想像成一個畫布。
The end of the canvas is fully automated,
畫布的末端是完全自動化的，
allowing AI to process the whole process.
允許 AI 處理整個過程。
In the middle, it may be strengthened,
在中間，可能會得到加強，
allowing AI to be your assistant,
允許 AI 成為你的助手，
to strengthen your ability.
來增強你的能力。
Then there is the agent,
然後是代理，
allowing AI to help you deal with some complicated things.
允許 AI 幫助你處理一些複雜的事情。
But the most important thing is
但最重要的是
that you must have a clear red line in your heart,
你必須在心中有一條清晰的紅線，
knowing that something is limited to humans.
知道什麼東西僅限於人類。
It is absolutely impossible to let go.
絕對不可能放手。
Okay, let's quickly summarize here.
好的，讓我們在這裡快速總結一下。
So what should a really smart AI assistant
那麼一個真正聰慧的 AI 助手
look like?
應該是什麼樣的呢？
Today, the most important concept
今天，最重要的概念
I think is this sentence.
我認為就是這句話。
Don't just leave the canvas to AI.
不要只是把畫布交給 AI。
The real cooperation is you being the driver,
真正的合作是你是駕駛者，
and AI is the smartest navigation system around you.
而 AI 是你身邊最聰慧的導航系統。
So your role must be transformed from a passive user
所以你的角色必須從被動使用者
to an active and strategic assistant.
轉變為主動的策略性助手。
So after we finished talking today,
所以在我們今天談完之後，
I also want to leave a question for you to think about.
我也想留給你一個問題來思考。
In your next project,
在你的下一個項目中，
what kind of role are you going to let AI play?
你打算讓 AI 扮演什麼樣的角色？
Is it just an obedient assistant?
只是一個聽話的助手嗎？
Or is it a convenient tool?
還是一個便利的工具？
Or can you improve it into
或者你能把它改進為
a strategic partner who can work with you?
一個可以與你合作的策略性合作夥伴？
I think how you answer this question
我認為你如何回答這個問題
will directly decide your future work outlook and efficiency.
將直接決定你未來的工作前景和效率。
I hope the framework we talked about today
我希望我們今天談論的框架
can help you find your answer.
能幫助你找到你的答案。
Okay, that's it for today.
好的，今天就到這裡。
Thank you for watching.
感謝你的觀看。
See you next time.
下次見。